Guide to the Thomas H. Foster and Catharine Osgood Foster Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Thomas H. Foster and Catharine Osgood Foster papers
1786-2005
1923-2005
YCAL MSS 812
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
34.56
(75 boxes) +1 broadside, 1 cold storage
Foster, Thomas H.
Foster, Catharine Osgood, 1907-
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Audiocassettes in boxes 48, 74: Use of original is restricted. Reference copy may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 49 (reel-to-reel audiotape and open reel film): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 77 (cold storage): Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. Consult the appropriate curator for further information.
Scope and Contents
The Thomas H. Foster and Catharine Osgood Foster Papers contain correspondence, writings, photographs, ephemera, audiovisual material, and printed material that document the professional and personal lives of the Fosters. Material includes writings that relate to Thomas Foster's career as a literary critic and scout for Farrar, Straus, and to Catharine Foster's books on gardening; documentation of the couple's leadership in the area of environmental stewardship; and records of their bird watching activity. Correspondence is both professional and personal in nature, and includes letters between Thomas and Catharine Foster, and some family correspondence. Printed material in the collection relates chiefly to early- and mid-twentieth century agriculture in New York and New England. Among the photographs in the collection are numerous slides depicting birds in their natural habitats, and journals of bird watching notes.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Thomas H. Foster, 1999-2005.
Arrangement
Organized into ten groupings: I. December 1999 Acquisition. II. December 1999 Acquisition. III. June 2000 Acquisition. IV. June 2000 Acquisition. V. July 2000 Acquisition. VI. January 2001 Acquisition. VII. October 2001 Acquisition. VIII. February 2005 Acquisition. IX. February 2005 Acquisition. X. April 2005 Acquisition.
Catharine Osgood Foster (1907-1998)
Catharine Farley Osgood born on April 26, 1907 in Newton Highlands, Massachusetts. She graduated from Mount Holyoke in 1930 and taught English at Bennington College from 1934 until 1969. She authored several books on gardening, including The Organic Gardener (New York, Vintage Books, 1972). She married Thomas H. Foster in 1937. Catharine Foster died on February 13, 1998 in Bennington, Vermont.
Thomas Henry Foster, Jr. (1907-2004)
Thomas Henry Foster, Jr. (1907-2004), American naturalist, literary critic, and poultry farmer, of Bennington, Vermont. He married Catharine Osgood in 1937.
Agriculture -- New England; Bird watching -- United States; Criticism -- United States; Critics -- United States; Environmentalism -- United States; Gardening -- United States; Organic gardening -- United States; Audiovisual materials -- United States -- 20th Century; Photographs -- United States -- 20th Century; Slides (photographs) -- United States -- 20th Century; Critics -- United States -- 20th Century; Foster, Thomas H.; Foster, Catharine Osgood, 1907-; Farrar, Straus, and Company
- December 1999 Acquisition, 1847-1999; 1; 24.8; (49 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  The first December 1999 Acquisition contains correspondence, writings, printed material, family papers, photographs, slides, and ephemera by or relating Thomas H. Foster and Catharine Osgood Foster. Writings include drafts of The Organic Gardener by Catharine Osgood Foster. Photographs include slides documenting Thomas Foster's birdwatching.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 49 (reel-to-reel audio tape, 8mm films): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Arrangement
  Organized under seven headings: Correspondence and Family Papers; Printed Material; Writings of Thomas Foster; Personal Papers; Writings of Catharine Foster; Photographs; Audiovisual Material.
  - Correspondence and Family Papers
    - Letters from Catharine Foster to Thomas Foster, 1941-1956; 9 (Box 1)
    - Solemnization of matrimony Thomas and Catharine Foster, 1937
    - Living will: Catharine Foster, 1989
    - Passports of Thomas Foster, 1946-1978; 2
    - Letters from Betty Downs, 1954-1969; 7
    - Thomas Foster's trip to England, Scotland and Ireland, 1946; 7
    - Letters from Isabel Martin, 1926-1958; 9
    - Letters from Isabel Martin, 1928-1958; 14 (Box 2)
    - Letters from Marian Stearns, 1928-1967, undated; 27
    - Letters from Eileen Parrinder, 1948-1989; 11 (Box 3)
    - Letters from Lily Merchant, 1948-1978; 13
    - Letters from Eileen Wilcox, 1960-1997; 7
    - Letters from Scott Hadley to Hannah Osgood (mother of Catharine Foster), 1929-1933; 5
    - Letters from Betty Downs, 1958-1963; 7
    - Letters from Hannah Osgood to her daughter Mrs. Thomas Foster, 1938-1943; 2
    - Letters from Thomas Foster to Catharine Foster, and to Mrs. Thomas H. Foster, Sr. (Thomas Foster's mother), 1958-1962; 3
    - Letters from Hubert Birdwood, 1966-1979
    - Letters from Rose Hindley, 1952-1963
    - Letters from Maria Hartley and Joan Ingilby, 1972-1983
    - Letters from Vera Moore, 1976-1982
    - Letters from I. M. Kenward, 1949-1981; 3
    - Letters from Grace Goodwin, 1947-1954
    - Letters from Catharine Foster to Hannah Osgood, undated (Box 4)
    - Letters from Catharine Foster to Hannah Osgood, 1950, undated
    - Letters from Catharine Foster to Thomas Foster, 1961
    - Letters from Hannah Osgood to Catharine Foster, 1929-1946; 3
    - Family and general correspondence, 1853-1950; 31
    - Family and general correspondence, 1951-1969; 33 (Box 5)
    - Family and general correspondence, 1970-1993; 41 (Box 6)
    - Family and general correspondence, 1994-1999; 13 (Box 7)
    - Greeting, Christmas, Easter and sympathy cards, 1950-1999; 9
    - Notes and unsorted correspondence, undated; 9
    - Blank postcards, undated; 3
    - Citations and art work
      - The 1990 Beyond War Award, 1990 December 8 (Box 8 (Oversize))
      - Bennington Garden Club certificate, 1968
      - Governor's Award, presented by the Conservation Society of Vermont, 1973
      - The Organic Gardener, cover art
        Cover art and photocopy of edited typeset from Knopf Pages 36-235
      - Herb Illustrations mounted on board
    - Farrar, Strauss & Giroux
      - Correspondence, royalty statements, and contracts for Thomas Foster, 1945-1996; 24 (Box 9)
      - Royalty statements, contracts and correspondence for Catharine Foster's book, The Organic Gardener, 1974-1987; 4
  - Printed Material
    - The Rural New Yorker, 1946-1948; 15 (Box 10 (Oversize))
    - The Rural New Yorker, 1948-1949; 17 (Box 11 (Oversize))
    - The Rural New Yorker, 1950-1954; 15 (Box 12 (Oversize))
    - The New England Homestead, 1946-1951; 12 (Box 13 (Oversize))
    - The New England Homestead, 1952-1955; 10 (Box 14 (Oversize))
    - The New York Times Magazine, 1970 August 9
    - The Boston Sunday Herald, 1861 (Box 15 (Oversize))
    - The Saturday Messenger, 1847-1848 (Box 16 (Oversize))
  - Writings of Thomas Foster
    - Amici Hiemis (Friends of Winter), Original autograph manuscript accompanied by publisher's correspondence, 1923 (Box 17)
    - Amici Hiemis (Friends of Winter), typescript, 1923
    - Amici Hiemis (Friends of Winter), carbon copy, 1923
    - Book Reviews, short stories and related correspondence, 1926-1966; 18
    - Newspaper clippings, 1930-1976; 4
    - Bank Statements and receipts, 1976-1981; 2
    - Miscellaneous papers and instruction books, 1940-1990; 2
    - The New York Herald Tribune Book Review containing reviews by Thomas Foster, 1926-1959; 18 (Box 18 (Oversize))
    - The New York Herald Tribune Book Review containing reviews by Thomas Foster, 1960-1962; 13 (Box 19 (Oversize))
    - The New York Times Book Review containing reviews by Thomas Foster, 1948-1960; 7 (Box 20 (Oversize))
    - The New York Times Book Review containing reviews by Thomas Foster, 1960-1999; 6 (Box 21 (Oversize))
  - Personal Papers
    - Thomas Foster, 3 notebooks listing "Books I Have Read", 1907-1926 (Box 22)
    - Diary, 1921-1922
    - Diary, 1922
    - School account, 1923
    - Journal listing college expenses, personal income and expenses, 1925-1947
    - Three spiral notepads containing address list, expenses and random notes, undated
    - Journal, 1925
    - Journal, 1926
    - Expenses, car trip, 1927
    - Three notebooks, 1951-1955
    - Notebooks, journals, and family information, 1947-1997; 8 (Box 23)
    - Journals, 1940-1985; 10 (Box 24)
    - University of South Caroliniana Society, 1979-1980; 2
    - Memorial service-John Swan, 1994
    - Obituary collection of writers, 1936-1996; 14
    - Obituary collection, 1990-1999; 8
    - Awards and certificates, 1970-1979
  - Writings of Catharine Foster
    - The Organic Gardener, original typescript, corrected, 1972; 5 (Box 25)
    - The Organic Gardener, typescript, corrected (photocopy), 1972; 4
    - Organic Flower Gardening, original edited typescript, 1975; 6
    - Plants-A-Plenty, original edited typescript, 1977; 6
    - General file folders, [1940-1990]; 7
    - General file folders, [1940-1990]; 26 (Box 26)
    - Writings on gardens, typescripts, corrected, 1983
    - Writings, autograph manuscript and typescript, undated; 2
    - Autograph manuscript notes, undated
    - Gardening clubs, conservation, 1965-1992
    - Miscellaneous, [1960-1990]; 2
    - Diaries, journals and spiral notebooks, 1919-1964; 6 (Box 27)
    - Food columns written by Catharine Foster for the Bennington Banner, 1980-1992; 6
    - "Around the Corner," a newspaper column written by Catharine Foster, 1966-1975; 9
    - "Around the Corner", 1976-1982; 7 (Box 28)
    - Newspaper Clippings, [1953-1981]; 3
    - Newsletters, bulletins, magazines, [1937-1990]; 6
    - "Around the Corner," clippings, 1976-1978 (Box 29 (Oversize))
    - The Organic Gardener, photocopy of edited typeset from Knopf, Pages 36-235, 1971
    - Horticultural card index, undated (Box 30)
    - Horticultural card index, undated (Box 31)
    - Horticultural card index, undated (Box 32)
    - New England Wildflower Society award, framed, 1992 November 15 (Box 33)
      Includes yellow camera filter, camera attachment, pencil sharpener, bird calendar for 1966, Vermont Antique car meet plaque, New Years card, and a photograph under beveled glass
    - Poem, framed, undated
    - Photograph, framed
    - Objects and ephemera
    - Tin box, undated
    - Shaker box, undated (Box 34)
    - Special correspondence "A" File, 1899-1953; 7 (Box 35)
    - Correspondence, 1950-1978; 3
  - Photographs
    - Early Family Photographs, 1905-1926; 3 (Box 36)
    - Family and Friends, 1928-1991; 2
    - Group Shots, 1965-1997, undated
    - Trip to England, undated
    - Family Dogs, 1940-1969, undated
    - Birds and Wildlife, 1949-1951, undated
    - Foliage, Trees and Gardens, 1949-1978, undated (Box 37)
    - Photographs, undated
    - Negatives and photographs, 9
    - Negatives and photographs, 1955-1958; 7 (Box 38)
    - Photographs (Box 39)
    - Framed photographs, 5
    - Slides, 1960
    - Slides, 1962-1977 (Box 40)
      Includes 2 Kodak Cover Glass transparencies
    - Slides, 1963-1977 (Box 41)
    - Slides, 1962-1986 (Box 42)
    - Slides, undated (Box 43)
    - Slides, 1968-1971 (Box 44)
    - Slides, 1959-1973 (Box 45)
    - Slides, 1964-1974 (Box 46)
    - Slides, 1962-1973 (Box 47)
  - Audiovisual Material
    Audiocassette in Box 48: Use of original is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    Box 49 (reel-to-reel audiotape and open reel film): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - "Kit Foster", undated; 1; 00:30:56; The program is distorted at times. High background noise and static can be heard on the tape. High frequency background noise can be heard as well. (Box 48, Item barcode 39002091248188)
    - "The Parable", Medieval Rehearsal / Production + Analysis, Kit Foster, undated; 1; 00:49:37; The program is distorted at times. There are severe speed fluctuations from 16:10 until the end of the audiotape reel. (Box 49, Item barcode 39002091248204)
    - "Dogs", 1957; 1 8mm film
    - "Fall Foliage", 1956; 1 8mm film
    - Untitled film, undated; 1 8mm film
- December 1999 Acquisition, 1786-1932; 2; 0.21; (1 box)
  The second December 1999 acquisition consists of newspapers dating to the eighteenth through twentieth centuries, some accompanied by correspondence.
  - Newspapers, 1786-1932; 7 (Box 50)
- June 2000 Acquisition, 1896-2000; 3; 3.46; (10 boxes) + 1 broadside
  The first June 2000 acquisition consists of correspondence, writings, personal papers, and photographs (including negatives and slides) by or relating to Thomas H. Foster and Catharine Osgood Foster. Personal papers include Osgood family correspondence and financial papers.
  - Correspondence
    - Thomas Foster to Catharine Osgood Foster, 1937-1954, undated; 2 (Box 51)
    - Thomas Foster to his mother, and others, 1944-1954
    - Catharine Osgood Foster to Mrs. G. L. Osgood, 1937 July 22
    - Letters to Thomas and Catharine Osgood Foster, 1950-1996; 3
    - Catharine Osgood Foster professional correspondence, from Bennington College and others, 1933-1997, undated; 3
    - Thomas Foster professional correspondence, 1949-2000, undated; 2
    - Third party correspondence, 1914-1971
    - Third party correspondence, to G. L. Osgood, 1928
    - Empty envelopes and blank postcards, undated
  - Personal and Financial Papers
    - Address book, undated (Box 52)
    - Birdwatching papers, pamphlets, 1954-1962, undated
    - Birth certificate (copy): Elizabeth Lewis Osgood, born 1900, 1958 June 26
    - Business cards: Thomas Foster, undated
    - Diary, 1988
    - Farley family tree, 1994 July 4
    - Attorney contract, 1935 January 16
    - Bank books, 1943-1963
    - Clearfield Trust Company correspondence, 1950
    - Charles L. Rogers estate, correspondence, 1933 May 5
    - Fanny Rogers estate, correspondence, 1942-1946
    - Receipts, 1923-1984; 3
    - Royalty statements, 1984-2000
    - Stock certificates, 1910-1929
    - Stock price letters, 1928-1950
    - Tax returns, 1931-1938
    - Francis Colburn exhibit program, 1984
    - Lock of hair: Mildred Foster, undated
    - Ephemera from trip to England, 1981
    - Minnesota Historical Society certificate, 1946 February 14
    - Catharine Foster, lecture notes and course registration cards from Mt. Holyoke College, undated; 3 (Box 53)
    - Notebook: Catharine Osgood and C. Patrick, Log of a bicycle trip to England, undated
    - Notebook: Catharine Osgood, with London address, undated
    - Puzzle contest, undated
    - Obituaries and Potter family genealogy notes, 1931-1998; 2
    - Passports: Catharine O. Foster, 1929-1988; 4
    - Wedding announcements, 1937
    - Sarah Chapman Francis Medal papers, 1972-1973
    - Diploma: Thomas Foster, Bennington High School, 1925 June 19
    - Diploma: Catharine F. Osgood, Mt. Holyoke College, 1931 June 9 (Box 54 (Oversize))
  - Photographs
    - Bread Loaf School, undated (Box 55 (Broadside))
    - Thomas Foster, Sr., 1896, undated (Box 56)
    - Thomas Foster, Jr., 1909-1990
    - Catharine O. Foster, 1923-1998
    - Catharine and Thomas Foster and others, 1937-1997, undated
    - Elizabeth Lewis Osgood, 1904-1924
    - Unidentified, undated; 13
    - Unidentified, undated; 7 (Box 57)
    - Negatives, undated; 9
    - Slides, 1980, undated; 10
    - Photograph album (Box 58 (Oversize))
    - Slides, undated (Box 59)
    - Slides, undated (Box 60)
  - Writings
    - Collection of British and American Authors, inscribed "now Catharine F. Osgood's", 1931 May (Box 61)
    - Richards, I. A. "A Statement on the Application of a Theory of Interpretation to General Education", 1935 December
    - Newspaper clippings, 1948-1974
    - T. Foster clippings, 1968-1974, undated
    - Foster, Catharine Osgood
      - Columns, 1978-1980
      - Book review, 1971
      - Report on conservation committee, 1975 October 28
- June 2000 Acquisition, 1833-1835, undated; 4; 0.29; (2 boxes)
  The second June 2000 acquisition consists of printed material, including Bibles inscribed to Thomas Foster by Susan Colgate and by Vincent Rain-Booth.
  - Bible, inscribed to Thomas Foster, 1921, undated (Box 62)
  - New Testament, inscribed to Thomas Foster, 1916, undated
  - The Sun, 1833 September 3 (Box 63 (Oversize))
  - Morning Herald, 1835 May 6
- July 2000 Acquisition, 1937-1997; 5; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  The July 2000 acquisition consists of photographs, a diary, clippings and other printed material, correspondence and ephemera relating to Thomas H. Foster and Catharine Osgood Foster.
  - Clippings and notes on bird watching, 1949-1955 (Box 64)
  - Writings, printed material, correspondence, 1937-1996
  - Julia Peterkin notes and correspondence, 1980-1997
  - Photograph album, 1999
  - Diary, including notes on bird watching, 1952-1961
  - Diary, 1942-1954 (Box 65)
- January 2001 Acquisition, 1959-2000; 6; 0.21; (1 box)
  The January 2001 acquisition consists of letters to Catharine Osgood Foster from Bernard Malamud, Wallace Fowlie and Eleanor Rockwell Edelstein.
  - Malamud, Bernard, 1959 November 2 (Box 66)
  - Fowlie, Wallace, 1994
  - Edelstein, Eleanor Rockwell, 1997-2000, undated
- October 2001 Acquisition, circa 1946-2001; 7; 1.33; (5 boxes)
  The October 2001 acquisition consists of correspondence, journals, photographs and printed material by or relating to Thomas H. Foster and Catharine Osgood Foster.
  - Application for Conservation Certificate for Mrs. Thomas Foster, circa 1967 (Box 67)
  - Correspondence between Thomas and Catharine Foster, circa 1974-1995
  - Unsorted correspondence, circa 1946-1994; 2
  - Journal of Catharine Osgood Foster, undated
  - Journal of Vermont trip, 1960
  - Notecards, undated; 3
  - Unidentified writings, undated
  - Newspaper Articles about Theodore Roethke, 2001
  - Photographs of Butterfly Habitat Garden, undated
  - Photograph and newspaper clipping of colt, 1970 May 16
  - Unsorted correspondence and writings, undated; 2 (Box 68)
  - Photographs and other papers, undated; 12
  - Plaque given to Tom Foster for outstanding service to Merck Forest and Farmland Center, circa 2000 (Box 69)
  - Writings, undated; 3 (Box 70)
  - Certificate of Acknowledgement to Thomas H. Foster by the Garden Club of America, 2000 (Box 71 (Oversize))
- February 2005 Acquisition, 1934-2004; 8; 3; (3 boxes) + 1 cold storage
  The first February 2005 acquisition consists of correspondence, diaries, printed material, photographs (including slides and negatives), an audio cassette, and memorabilia by or relating to Thomas H. Foster and Catharine Osgood Foster.
  Audiocassette in box 74: Use of original is restricted. Reference copy may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Box 77 (cold storage): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies have been substituted in the main files. Consult the appropriate curator for further information.
  - Correspondence, 1998-2004; 30 (Box 72)
  - Correspondence, 1951-2004; 18 (Box 73)
  - Diaries, 1934-2003, undated; 7 (Box 73)
  - "Tom and Rob," phone conversation, circa 2003; 1; 03:09:27; High background noise can be heard on the tape. A high amount of hiss can also be heard. The program is mostly background noise. It is distorted at times. (Box 48, Item barcode 39002091248196)
  - Bookmark, undated (Box 74)
  - Ornament, 2000
  - Printed material, 1979-2003
  - Programs, 1950-1979
  - "Denial," poem by Stephen Sandy, printed, 2003 December
  - Silo, 1998
  - Paul Harris Fellow, medal, undated
  - Paul Harris Fellow, award, undated
  - Slides, 1963-1970
  - Photographs, 1972-1982, undated; 3
  - Photographic negatives, undated (Box 77 (cold storage))
    Box 77 (cold storage): Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. Consult the appropriate curator for further information.
- February 2005 Acquisition, 2001-2004; 9; 0.42; (1 box)
  The second February 2005 acquisition consists of correspondence, including Christmas cards and birthday cards, and accompanying printed material.
  - Correspondence, 2001-2004; 12 (Box 75)
- April 2005 Acquisition, 1999; 10; 0.21; (1 box)
  The April 2005 acquisition consists of notes, printouts of photographs, maps, printed material, receipts and other papers relating to a trip to California made by Thomas H. Foster.
  - California trip, 1999 April; 3 (Box 76)